<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
 <title>Tom Preston-Werner</title>
 <link href="http://tom.preston-werner.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://tom.preston-werner.com/"/>
 <updated>2009-05-04T11:38:53+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://tom.preston-werner.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Tom Preston-Werner</name>
   <email>tom@mojombo.com</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Blogging Like a Hacker</title>
   <link href="http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/11/17/blogging-like-a-hacker.html"/>
   <updated>2008-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/11/17/blogging-like-a-hacker</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Blogging Like a Hacker&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p class="meta"&gt;17 Nov 2008 &amp;#8211; San Francisco&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2000, when I thought I was going to be a professional writer, I spent hours a day on LiveJournal doing writing practice with other aspiring poets and authors. Since then I&amp;#8217;ve blogged at three different domains about web standards, print design, photography, Flash, illustration, information architecture, ColdFusion, package management, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PHP&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt;, advertising, Ruby, Rails, and Erlang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love writing. I get a kick out of sharing my thoughts with others. The act of transforming ideas into words is an amazingly efficient way to solidify and refine your thoughts about a given topic. But as much as I enjoy blogging, I seem to be stuck in a cycle of quitting and starting over. Before starting the current iteration, I resolved to do some introspection to determine the factors that were leading to this destructive pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already knew a lot about what I &lt;strong&gt;didn&amp;#8217;t&lt;/strong&gt; want. I was tired of complicated blogging engines like WordPress and Mephisto. I wanted to write great posts, not style a zillion template pages, moderate comments all day long, and constantly lag behind the latest software release. Something like Posterous looked attractive, but I wanted to style my blog, and it needed to be hosted at the domain of my choosing. For the same reason, other hosted sites (wordpress.com, blogger.com) were disqualified. There are a few people directly using GitHub as a blog (which is very cool), but that&amp;#8217;s a bit too much of an impedance mismatch for my tastes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, October 19th, I sat down in my San Francisco apartment with a glass of apple cider and a clear mind. After a period of reflection, I had an idea. While I&amp;#8217;m not specifically trained as an author of prose, I &lt;strong&gt;am&lt;/strong&gt; trained as an author of code. What would happen if I approached blogging from a software development perspective? What would that look like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, all my writing would be stored in a Git repository. This would ensure that I could try out different ideas and explore a variety of posts all from the comfort of my preferred editor and the command line. I&amp;#8217;d be able to publish a post via a simple deploy script or post-commit hook. Complexity would be kept to an absolute minimum, so a static site would be preferable to a dynamic site that required ongoing maintenance. My blog would need to be easily customizable; coming from a graphic design background means I&amp;#8217;ll always be tweaking the site&amp;#8217;s appearance and layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last month I&amp;#8217;ve brought these concepts to fruition and I&amp;#8217;m pleased to announce &lt;a href="http://github.com/mojombo/jekyll"&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;. Jekyll is a simple, blog aware, static site generator. It takes a template directory (representing the raw form of a website), runs it through Textile and Liquid converters, and spits out a complete, static website suitable for serving with Apache or your favorite web server. If you&amp;#8217;re reading this on the website (http://tom.preston-werner.com), you&amp;#8217;re seeing a Jekyll generated blog!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand how this all works, open up my &lt;a href="http://github.com/mojombo/tpw"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TPW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; repo in a new browser window. I&amp;#8217;ll be referencing the code there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at &lt;a href="http://github.com/mojombo/tpw/tree/master/index.html"&gt;index.html&lt;/a&gt;. This file represents the homepage of the site. At the top of the file is a chunk of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YAML&lt;/span&gt; that contains metadata about the file. This data tells Jekyll what layout to give the file, what the page&amp;#8217;s title should be, etc. In this case, I specify that the &amp;#8220;default&amp;#8221; template should be used. You can find the layout files in the &lt;a href="http://github.com/mojombo/tpw/tree/master/_layouts"&gt;_layouts&lt;/a&gt; directory. If you open &lt;a href="http://github.com/mojombo/tpw/tree/master/_layouts/default.html"&gt;default.html&lt;/a&gt; you can see that the homepage is constructed by wrapping index.html with this layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;ll also notice Liquid templating code in these files. &lt;a href="http://www.liquidmarkup.org/"&gt;Liquid&lt;/a&gt; is a simple, extensible templating language that makes it easy to embed data in your templates. For my homepage I wanted to have a list of all my blog posts. Jekyll hands me a Hash containing various data about my site. A reverse chronological list of all my blog posts can be found in &lt;code&gt;site.posts&lt;/code&gt;. Each post, in turn, contains various fields such as &lt;code&gt;title&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;date&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jekyll gets the list of blog posts by parsing the files in the &lt;a href="http://github.com/mojombo/tpw/tree/master/_posts"&gt;_posts&lt;/a&gt; directory. Each post&amp;#8217;s filename contains the publishing date and slug (what shows up in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt;) that the final &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; file should have. Open up the file corresponding to this blog post: &lt;a href="http://github.com/mojombo/tpw/tree/master/_posts/2008-11-17-blogging-like-a-hacker.textile"&gt;2008-11-17-blogging-like-a-hacker.textile&lt;/a&gt;. GitHub renders textile files by default, so to better understand the file, click on the &lt;a href="http://github.com/mojombo/tpw/tree/master/_posts/2008-11-17-blogging-like-a-hacker.textile?raw=true"&gt;raw&lt;/a&gt; view to see the original file. Here I&amp;#8217;ve specified the &lt;code&gt;post&lt;/code&gt; layout. If you look at that file you&amp;#8217;ll see an example of a nested layout. Layouts can contain other layouts allowing you a great deal of flexibility in how pages are assembled. In my case I use a nested layout in order to show related posts for each blog entry. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YAML&lt;/span&gt; also specifies the post&amp;#8217;s title which is then embedded in the post&amp;#8217;s body via Liquid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posts are handled in a special way by Jekyll. The date you specify in the filename is used to construct the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt; in the generated site. This post, for instance, ends up at &lt;code&gt;http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/11/17/blogging-like-a-hacker.html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Files that do not reside in directories prefixed with an underscore are mirrored into a corresponding directory structure in the generated site. If a file does not have a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YAML&lt;/span&gt; preface, it is not run through the Liquid interpreter. Binary files are copied over unmodified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to convert your raw site into the finished version, you simply run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="terminal"&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ jekyll /path/to/raw/site /path/to/place/generated/site&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is still a very young project. I&amp;#8217;ve only developed the exact functionality that I&amp;#8217;ve needed. As time goes on I&amp;#8217;d like to see the project mature and support additional features. If you end up using Jekyll for your own blog, drop me a line and let me know what you&amp;#8217;d like to see in future versions. Better yet, fork the project over at GitHub and hack in the features yourself!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been living with Jekyll for just over a month now. I love it. Driving the development of Jekyll based on the needs of my blog has been very rewarding. I can edit my posts in TextMate, giving me automatic and competent spell checking. I have immediate and first class access to the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt; and page templates. Everything is backed up on GitHub. I feel a lightness now when I&amp;#8217;m writing a post. The system is simple enough that I can keep the entire conversion process in my head. The distance from my brain to my blog has shrunk, and, in the end, I think that will make me a better author.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How to Meet Your Next Cofounder</title>
   <link href="http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/11/03/how-to-meet-your-next-cofounder.html"/>
   <updated>2008-11-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/11/03/how-to-meet-your-next-cofounder</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;How to Meet Your Next Cofounder&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p class="meta"&gt;3 Nov 2008 &amp;#8211; San Francisco&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few months I&amp;#8217;ve seen a number of people looking for cofounders on Hacker News or via their own personal blogs. I think this is, at best, a highly inefficient way to find a cofounder and, at worst, a way to fool yourself into finding the &lt;strong&gt;wrong&lt;/strong&gt; cofounder. In any case, it&amp;#8217;s a naive approach to finding the person that will need to stand by your side in the coming storm that we call &amp;#8220;running a startup.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t get me wrong, the internet is an amazing tool for meeting people. The wider the net you cast, the more likely you are to find the perfect match. But the internet has its limitations. I&amp;#8217;ve had internet friends that were engaging, witty, and brilliant online, but in person felt awkward and boring. Conversely, I know people that are volatile and inflammatory online, but present an attitude of friendliness and caring in person. This phenomenon makes it difficult to gauge an individual&amp;#8217;s personality from online interaction alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A far better use of the internet is to find groups of people that share your interests. Track down the local users group for your language or technology of choice. The simple fact that members of these groups take time out of their day to show up means that they&amp;#8217;re more motivated and driven than the average person. Even if it&amp;#8217;s a bit of a commute to get to the meetings, start showing up regularly. Prepare a few presentations on topics that you&amp;#8217;re passionate about. Bonus points if you present on ideas related to your potential startup. Don&amp;#8217;t worry about revealing your game-changing secrets; stealth mode is bullshit. Talk to everyone. Steer the conversation toward your interests and if someone there is excited about the same things, it will be clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may take weeks or months, but in a good group you&amp;#8217;ll find a handful of people that you really like. If at all possible, go out drinking with these people after the meetups. This is one of the easiest ways to go from &amp;#8220;acquaintance&amp;#8221; to &amp;#8220;friend&amp;#8221; and gives you free license to bring up your craziest of ideas without sounding like too much of a nutjob.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of the people that you like, several may make excellent candidates for cofounders. Do a little research on these individuals. What does their code look like? Have they done much open source? Do they demonstrate an entrepreneurial spirit? Can they stick with a single project for a long time? Have they been loyal to their friends and companies in the past? A good cofounder should be someone with whom you feel privileged to work. And they should feel privileged to work with you. The two of you should be on very solid ground before you begin your startup adventure, because once you do, the impact of every argument is going to feel like it&amp;#8217;s been multiplied by a thousand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all sounds like a lot of hard work. Maybe you&amp;#8217;re wondering if it would be better to just go solo. I did that with Gravatar, and, in retrospect, it&amp;#8217;s painfully obvious that I made a lot of stupid mistakes. When it&amp;#8217;s just you and your thoughts it becomes too easy to pick the first thing that pops into your head. We&amp;#8217;re programmed to think all of our ideas are good, but reality tells a different story. Truly good decisions are forged from the furnace of argument, not plucked like daisies from the pasture of a peaceful mind. A good cofounder tells you when your ideas are half-baked and ensures that your good ideas actually get implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second biggest danger with going solo is the loss of motivation. Solipsism might make you feel important at first, but the constant lack of feedback and the absence of support during tough times can easily lead to a premature end to your adventure. Cofounders are like workout buddies. Just when you think there&amp;#8217;s no possible way you can do another rep, there they are, rooting you on toward an achievement that wouldn&amp;#8217;t be possible without them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your choice of cofounder will affect everything you do in your startup. They&amp;#8217;ll share every defeat with you and celebrate every success. They&amp;#8217;ll help you understand your own ideas better by offering a different perspective. They&amp;#8217;ll be the single most important decision you make during the tenure of your startup, so choose wisely and with extreme care.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Looking back on Selling Gravatar to Automattic</title>
   <link href="http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/10/27/looking-back-on-selling-gravatar-to-automattic.html"/>
   <updated>2008-10-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
   <id>http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/10/27/looking-back-on-selling-gravatar-to-automattic</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Looking back on Selling Gravatar to Automattic&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p class="meta"&gt;23 Oct 2008 &amp;#8211; San Francisco&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For an entrepreneur, the line between horrible mistake and runaway success can be so thin that even Kate Moss would be envious. I lived with &lt;a href="http://gravatar.com/"&gt;Gravatar&lt;/a&gt; for nearly four years before that line even became thick enough to measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it&amp;#8217;s become one of my favorite parables, I&amp;#8217;ll save the details of how I came up with the idea for Gravatar for a future post. What&amp;#8217;s important to know is that the idea was spawned not from a business perspective, but from a desperate desire to create something new in the world of blogging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spin the clock back four years and you&amp;#8217;ll find me sitting at my Windows desktop machine in my underwear with a box of Life cereal to my left and a day old Coke to my right. Since I&amp;#8217;d been laid off from my job as a Java developer some months earlier, I&amp;#8217;d decided to take the entrepreneurial plunge doing what I knew best: web design. Working in a cone of isolation, I&amp;#8217;d become accustomed to waking up late, swinging my legs over the right side of the bed, and in one fluid movement sliding over to the ratty chair I stole from my old college dorm room. I&amp;#8217;d spend most of the day working on client projects in ColdFusion or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PHP&lt;/span&gt;. It was hard work and could become a bit tiresome. I needed an outlet, something that didn&amp;#8217;t have a suit on the other end of a telephone telling me how blue was the wrong color and things would be so much better if only the photo had a slightly bigger border. Gravatar would become that outlet for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really big into web standards at the time, having recently read Zeldman&amp;#8217;s seminal work, and became a true believer. Eric Meyers, Dan Cederholm, and Jon Hicks became like gods to me. I worked very hard at making relevant and witty comments around the right kinds of blogs. Being a part of that movement became a significant goal for me. My Movable Type weblog rarely went more than two days days without a post on design or standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two weeks after I had the idea for Gravatar the first version was written and deployed. Every request hit the database and dynamically generated a properly sized gravatar via PHP&amp;#8217;s gd2 api. Premature optimization and all that, right? The first thing I did after getting the system to a workable state was email all the bloggers I looked up to (and that had no idea who I was). Blog comments at the time were a pretty dreary affair and I guess Cederholm was intrigued enough by my idea that he linked to it in a sidebar micro-post on simplebits.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That single mention kicked off a slow but steady trickle of interest in the system. A few blogs here and there installed the plugin and the world started seeing avatars that mysteriously followed them around. At the same time, just as people must have thought Cheez Whiz was a stupid idea when it first came out, some bloggers started railing against Gravatar, calling it frivolous, inefficient, and &amp;#8220;an abomination.&amp;#8221; This was my first nibble at the smorgasbord of what was to become the &amp;#8220;horrible mistake&amp;#8221; aspect of Gravatar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the inherently self-advertising nature of gravatars (the &amp;#8220;what the hell is that and how do I get one?&amp;#8221; brand of advertising), Gravatar adoption increased at a rapid rate. Having crafted the idea for Gravatar without any semblance of business model or growth projection or build-out strategy, things took a rather dramatic dive away from &amp;#8220;runaway success&amp;#8221; as my server (yes, singular) buckled under the pressure of tens of requests per second! As it turns out, regenerating a gravatar on every request is not very &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPU&lt;/span&gt; efficient. Gravatars worldwide suddenly turned into little red Xs. Then, in what has become known as the Twitter Effect, a barrage of emails hit me complaining about how the free service on which they had come to depend was down, and how this would adversely impact my well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fixed the code. Gravatar came back online with caching. All the while I&amp;#8217;d had the bright idea that gravatars would be rated for content, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MPAA&lt;/span&gt;-style. Because users clearly were not fit to rate their own images, I was manually rating 400 or more avatars each day. If I missed a day, I&amp;#8217;d have damn near a thousand waiting for me the next day. In addition to the angry mob, I was very fortunate to have an amazingly supportive group of users that volunteered to help me rate images. I owe them my sanity, and it freed up enough time for me to work on the next iteration of the site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G2, as I called it, would be written in Rails and use lighttpd plus a convoluted directory structure of symlinks to enable me to pre-render every gravatar (1&amp;#215;1 up to 80&amp;#215;80) and serve only static images. I did this to avoid having to rent or buy the kind of hardware necessary to hook up a properly scaled system. Up until the end I ran Gravatar on a maximum of two rented commodity servers that set me back a mere $300/month, a pittance for the kind of traffic I was serving. I say it was a pittance, but that&amp;#8217;s not really true. Donations didn&amp;#8217;t even come close to covering that cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point early in the development of G2, Toni Schneider, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CEO&lt;/span&gt; of Automattic (the company behind WordPress.com and Akismet) contacted me after hearing my &lt;a href="http://blog.gravatar.com/2007/10/18/automattic-gravatar/"&gt;interview about the future of Gravatar&lt;/a&gt; on the WordPress podcast. This was exciting news! How perfect a fit would it be for Gravatar to be bought by Automattic? I was already planning a trip up to San Francisco to meet with the Powerset guys, so the timing worked out perfectly for me to meet in person with Toni. I ended up having lunch with Toni and Matt Mullenweg at 21st Ammendment on 2nd Street. It was a bit intimidating to come to the mecca of tech startups to meet with such huge players in the blogging community. Turned out that both Matt and Toni are great guys and so we had drinks for about two hours, talking about my ideas for Gravatar and how we might be able to work together. Everything seemed great&amp;#8212;I was jazzed and they seemed excited&amp;#8212;but a few weeks later Toni let me know that the timing was wrong and they couldn&amp;#8217;t make a play at that time. He suggested I proceed with G2 and they&amp;#8217;d proceed with their own avatar system. I was pretty bummed about the outcome, but I took their advice and kept going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks before G2 was finished, the site imploded in a big way. One machine. Hundreds of requests per second. That poor &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CPU&lt;/span&gt; must have thought it was the End Times. Instead of wasting time on getting the existing system back up, I put on my headphones, turned it up to eleven, and got back to work on G2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m not sure if you&amp;#8217;ve ever had to work on a project while your users are publicly skewering you on your blog for allowing the service to go down, but it&amp;#8217;s as close to depression as I&amp;#8217;ve ever come. If I&amp;#8217;d had less pride, I would have popped everyone a huge middle finger and let the service die, but instead I waded through the hundreds of comments and deleted the ones with threats, hatred, or my favorite, the words &amp;#8220;fuck you&amp;#8221; repeated 600 times. It wasn&amp;#8217;t fair, I told myself, that I should be sitting here with high blood pressure trying to raise Gravatar from the dead while the unappreciative masses do what they do best on the internet. The only thing that kept me going was never being able to tell which side of the mistake/success boundary I was sitting on. It was hard to think of the situation as anything but a huge failure, but the shitstorm the downtime was causing indicated that people found the service valuable. I want to say that Twitter went through the same thing, but they suffered their downtime with millions of dollars in the bank. The only thing I had was a full time job unrelated to Gravatar and a credit card that reminded me every month of my bad judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally G2 was done, deployed, and fully operational. I have no idea how many users I lost due to the several weeks of downtime, but I don&amp;#8217;t think it was very many. There seems to be a corollary to the Twitter Effect that I&amp;#8217;d call the Forgiveness Effect. It dictates that if a user enjoys a free service and that service is currently up, all past atrocities will be easily and quickly forgiven. With the site running again, things looked to be shifting back towards a success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things were not all rainbows and unicorns though. My Rube Goldbergian architecture had a few quirks that needed to be dealt with. The site still had some elusive bugs from the overly-rapid development cycle. And just like new lanes on freeways always fill up immediately, the two new servers I was running started causing expensive bandwidth overages. I had taken a job at Powerset at this point and the combined pressures of these two commitments started to weigh me down. Once again I started feeling like all the effort I put into Gravatar was for nothing. Like I would never benefit from any of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a last ditch effort to save Gravatar from final doom, I emailed Toni and pitched him again on Gravatar. I figured it was a long shot, but what the hell, couldn&amp;#8217;t hurt. Things must have changed in the prior 6 months because Toni was very receptive to the idea. We met again, at 21st Ammendment, and hashed out a tentative deal over drinks. I&amp;#8217;d never sold anything like this before, so my technique was probably very amateurish. I&amp;#8217;m almost certain I could have gotten a better deal out of it, but I had the smell of desperation about me and I really did want to see Gravatar end up in Automattic&amp;#8217;s hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four days later, Automattic made their official offer. On September 21st, 2007 we inked the deal and Gravatar became both the first company that I ever sold and the first company that Automattic ever acquired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am quite satisfied with the sale to Automattic. Some will say that I should have pursued VC funding. Indeed, I was contacted by several firms but never travelled very far down that road. I always felt like Gravatar was a feature, and I wasn&amp;#8217;t comfortable building a company on such a tiny foundation. Reinforcing this decision, no viable business model ever coalesced during the time I was building the site. It was also made clear by Toni that Automattic would maintain Gravatar as a separate brand and continue its evolution (instead of just absorbing it into WordPress). This appealed to my ego. Most companies kill or maim everything they acquire, but here was a chance for Gravatar to carry forward with all of Automattic&amp;#8217;s resources behind it (instead of two measly servers). Part of me just wanted to see what Gravatar could become with time, money, and man-power moving it forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things always seem so clear in retrospect. But it was pride and persistence that kept me in the game long enough to have anything to look back on at all. While the line between horrible mistake and runaway success may be difficult to see, you can still find it if you look hard enough.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How I Turned Down $300,000 from Microsoft to go Full-Time on GitHub</title>
   <link href="http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/10/18/how-i-turned-down-300k.html"/>
   <updated>2008-10-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/10/18/how-i-turned-down-300k</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;How I Turned Down $300,000 from Microsoft to go Full-Time on GitHub&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p class="meta"&gt;18 Oct 2008 &amp;#8211; San Francisco&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2008 is a leap year. That means that three hundred and sixty six days ago, almost to the minute, I was sitting alone in a booth at Zeke&amp;#8217;s Sports Bar and Grill on 3rd Street in San Francisco. I wouldn&amp;#8217;t normally hang out at a sports bar, let alone a sports bar in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SOMA&lt;/span&gt;, but back then Thursday was &amp;#8220;I Can Has Ruby&amp;#8221; night. I guess back then &amp;#8220;I can has _______&amp;#8221; was also a reasonable moniker to attach to pretty much anything. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ICHR&lt;/span&gt; was a semi-private meeting of like minded Ruby Hackers that generally and willingly devolved into late night drinking sessions. Normally these nights would fade away like my hangover the next morning, but this night was different. This was the night that &lt;a href="http://github.com/"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; was born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I was sitting at the booth alone because I&amp;#8217;d just ordered a fresh Fat Tire and needed a short break from the socializing that was happening over at the long tables in the dimly lit aft portion of the bar. On the fifth or sixth sip, Chris Wanstrath walked in. I have trouble remembering now if I&amp;#8217;d even classify Chris and I as &amp;#8220;friends&amp;#8221; at the time. We knew each other through Ruby meetups and conferences, but only casually. Like a mutual &amp;#8220;hey, I think your code is awesome&amp;#8221; kind of thing. I&amp;#8217;m not sure what made me do it, but I gestured him over to the booth and said &amp;#8220;dude, check this out.&amp;#8221; About a week earlier I&amp;#8217;d started work on a project called &lt;a href="http://github.com/mojombo/grit"&gt;Grit&lt;/a&gt; that allowed me to access Git repositories in an object oriented manner via Ruby code. Chris was one of only a handful of Rubyists at the time that was starting to become serious about Git. He sat down and I started showing him what I had. It wasn&amp;#8217;t much, but it was enough to see that it had sparked something in Chris. Sensing this, I launched into my half-baked idea for some sort of website that acted as hub for coders to share their Git repositories. I even had a name: GitHub. I may be paraphrasing, but his response was along the lines of a very emphatic &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;m in. Let&amp;#8217;s do it!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next night, Friday, October 19, 2007 at 10:24pm Chris made the first commit to the GitHub repository and sealed in digital stone the beginning of our joint venture. There were, so far, no agreements of any kind regarding how things would proceed. Just two guys that decided to hack together on something that sounded cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember those amazing few minutes in Karate Kid where Daniel is training to become a martial arts expert? Remember the music? Well, you should probably go buy and listen to &lt;a href="http://phobos.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewAlbum?i=260417864&amp;amp;id=260417040&amp;amp;s=143441"&gt;You&amp;#8217;re The Best&lt;/a&gt; by Joe Esposito in iTunes because I&amp;#8217;m about to hit you with a montage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the next three months Chris and I spent ridiculous hours planning and coding GitHub. I kept going with Grit and designed the UI. Chris built out the Rails app. We met in person every Saturday to make design decisions and try to figure out what the hell our pricing plan would look like. I remember one very rainy day we talked for a good two hours about various pricing strategies over some of the best Vietnamese egg rolls in the city. All of this we did while holding other engagements. I, for one, was employed full time at Powerset as a tools developer for the Ranking and Relevance team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In mid January, after three months of nights and weekends, we launched into private beta mode, sending invites to our friends. In mid February PJ Hyett joined in and made us three-strong. We publicly launched the site on April 10th. TechCrunch was not invited. At this point it was still just three 20-somethings without a single penny of outside investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was still working full time at Powerset on July 1, 2008 when we learned that Powerset had just been acquired by Microsoft for around $100 million. This was interesting timing. With the acquisition, I was going to be faced with a choice sooner than I had anticipated. I could either sign on as a Microsoft employee or quit and go GitHub full time. At 29 years old, I was the oldest of the three GitHubbers, and had accumulated a proportionally larger amount of debt and monthly expenditure. I was used to my six digit lifestyle. Further confounding the issue was the imminent return of my wife, Theresa, from her PhD fieldwork in Costa Rica. I would soon be transitioning from make-believe bachelor back to married man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To muddy the waters of decision even more, the Microsoft employment offer was juicy. Salary + $300k over three years juicy. That&amp;#8217;s enough money to make anybody think twice about anything. So I was faced with this: a safe job with lots of guaranteed money as a Microsoft man &amp;#8211;or&amp;#8211; a risky job with unknown amounts of money as an entrepreneur. I knew things with the other GitHub guys would become extremely strained if I stayed on at Powerset much longer. Having saved up some money and become freelancers some time ago, they had both started dedicating full time effort to GitHub. It was do or die time. Either pick GitHub and go for it, or make the safe choice and quit GitHub to make wheelbarrows full of cash at Microsoft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want a recipe for restless sleep, I can give you one. Add one part &amp;#8220;what will my wife think&amp;#8221; with 3,000 parts Benjamin Franklin; stir in a &amp;#8220;beer anytime you damn well please&amp;#8221; and top with a chance at financial independence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve become pretty good at giving my employers the bad news that I&amp;#8217;m leaving the company to go do something cooler. I broke the news to my boss at Powerset on the day the employment offer was due. I told him I was quitting to go work full time on GitHub. Like any great boss, he was bummed, but understanding. He didn&amp;#8217;t try to tempt me with a bigger bonus or anything. I think deep down he knew I was going to leave. I may have even received a larger incentive to stay than others, on account of my being a flight risk. Those Microsoft managers are crafty, I tell you. They&amp;#8217;ve got retention bonuses down to a science. Well, except when you throw an entrepreneur, the singularity of the business world, into the mix. Everything goes wacky when you&amp;#8217;ve got one of those around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, just as Indiana Jones could never turn down the opportunity to search for the Holy Grail, I could no less turn down the chance to work for myself on something I truly love, no matter how safe the alternative might be. When I&amp;#8217;m old and dying, I plan to look back on my life and say &amp;#8220;wow, that was an adventure,&amp;#8221; not &amp;#8220;wow, I sure felt safe.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
 </entry>
 
 
</feed>